<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An indictment against tythes: or, Tythes no wages for Gospel-ministers: wherein is declared, I. The time when tythes were first given in England. II. By whom, and by whose authority and power tythes were first by a law established in England. III. To whom, and to what end and purpose tythes were first given, and after continued in England. IV. Ministers pretending a threefold right to tythes, 1. By donation. 2. By the laws of the nation. And 3. By the Law of God; examined and confuted ... To which are added, certain reasons taken out of Doctor Burgess his Case, concerning the buying of bishops lands, which are as full and directly against tythes, as to what he applied them. Likewise a query to William Prynne. By John Canne. By John Osborne, a lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</title>
            <author>Osborne, John, lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863128</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863128</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An indictment against tythes: or, Tythes no wages for Gospel-ministers: wherein is declared, I. The time when tythes were first given in England. II. By whom, and by whose authority and power tythes were first by a law established in England. III. To whom, and to what end and purpose tythes were first given, and after continued in England. IV. Ministers pretending a threefold right to tythes, 1. By donation. 2. By the laws of the nation. And 3. By the Law of God; examined and confuted ... To which are added, certain reasons taken out of Doctor Burgess his Case, concerning the buying of bishops lands, which are as full and directly against tythes, as to what he applied them. Likewise a query to William Prynne. By John Canne. By John Osborne, a lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</title>
                  <author>Osborne, John, lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</author>
                  <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Livewel Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (Thomason Tracts E.989[28]) and the Goldsmith Library, University of London (Goldsmiths'-Kress library of economic literature: 106:1453).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665. --  Case concerning the buying of bishops lands.</term>
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN INDICTMENT Againſt TYTHES: OR, Tythes no Wages for Goſpel-Miniſters: Wherein is declared,
<list>
                  <item>I. The time when Tythes were firſt given in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. By whom, and by whoſe Authority and power Tythes were firſt by a Law eſtabliſhed in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. To whom, and to what end and purpoſe Tythes were firſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and after continued in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. Miniſters pretending a threefold Right to Tythes, 1. By Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. 2. By the Laws of the Nation. And 3. By the Law of God; examined and confuted.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Osborne,</hi> a Lover of the Truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>To which are added, Certain Reaſons taken out of Doctor <hi>Burgeſs</hi> his CASE, concerning The buying of BISHOPS LANDS, Which are as full and directly againſt Tythes, as to what he applied them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe a QUERY to <hi>William Prynne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN CANNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Micah 3. 5.</bibl> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets that deceive my people, and bite them with their teeth, and cry Peace; but if a man put not into their mouths, they prepare war againſt him.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 57. 14.</bibl> 
               <hi>And he ſhall ſay, Caſt ye up, prepare the way, take up the ſtumbling-block out of the way of my people.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley. 1659</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115310:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115310:2"/>
               <hi>To the Supreme Authority, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>now ſitting at</hi> Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>FOraſmuch as it hath pleaſed the great Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, who is the onely wiſe Diſpoſer of all things, to re-call You to Your Places, from whence You were unjuſtly depoſed by an Uſurped Power; Therefore I beſeech You conſider, that great things are now expected from You: And I do humbly intreat and beſeech You, that You will be pleaſed to act prudently and vigorouſly for the Glory of GOD, the Peace and Tranquillity of this Nation, and the Comfort, Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of all the faithful Servants of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, within this Commonwealth. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ſome grievances and preſſures reſt upon the hearts and Spirits of many Godly, Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious People of this Land; and one eſpecially up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mine own Spirit and Conſcience in particular, (as well as upon divers others) I mean that unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable burden of Tythes, ſo diſhonorable to God, and deſtructive to his true Worſhip, and ſo much tending to the abaſement of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the advancement of the power and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> This, I ſay, is a grievance neceſſary to be conſidered, and ſpeedily
<pb facs="tcp:115310:3"/>
reformed; Becauſe I do not finde any Warrant in in the Word of God, to uphold Miniſter Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by Tythes. And therefore, I, as a Lover of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, and as an obedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Subject to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, do exhort and beſeech You, that You will have a tender care and compaſſion upon all fad oppreſſed Souls. And to ſtir You up thereunto, am bold to offer to Your view the ſhort enſuing Treatiſe, humbly deſiring that You will be pleaſed to read it deliberately, and conſider it ſeriouſly: and to make it a chief part of Your work, according to the counſel of the Lord, by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 6. <hi>To looſe the bands of wickedneſſ, to take off the heavy burdens, and let the oppreſſed go free, and that You break every yoke.</hi> And then in ſo doing, God will bleſs You in all Your conſultations and actions.</p>
            <p>But I beſeech You miſtake not my good intent and meaning herein: For I purpoſe not to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to teach You Your Duties in Your places and callings; but to inform You of ſuch a growing evil in this Commonwealth, as if it be not timely ſuppreſſed, may ſpeedily draw down the wrath and judgements of God upon this Nation.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I deſire to ſtir up your mindes, that by your godly actings and proceedings, God may be glorified, your own ſouls comforted, and poor oppreſſed Conſciences relieved.</p>
            <p>Which ſhall ever be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, John Osborne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115310:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Few months before the <hi>ſitting of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In a Book Intituled, <hi>A two-fold Shaking of the Earth.</hi>
               </note> I declared my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning the <hi>late Government by a Single Perſon,</hi> or the <hi>Second State-Apoſtacy;</hi> that is, how it ſhould be plucket up root and branch, by the Repreſentatives of the People. This <hi>Repreſentative of the People,</hi> (whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they ſhould be, for I poſitively pitched upon none) I took to be the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> in <hi>Rev. 11. 13.</hi> Now ſo it is (and bleſſed be the Lord for it) we ſee the ſame is come to paſſ, to the great joy and comfort of all upright ones every where.</p>
            <p>This bleſſed of the Lord (which is marvelous in our eyes) not onely ſtrengthens me in my former opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> is begun: but likewiſe what I have there ſpoken concerning the <hi>effects</hi> of that <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> (as to <hi>Tythes, the carnal Church, Miniſtry, Worſhip and Government,</hi> with all the <hi>corrupt Laws of the Nation)</hi> will in ſome ſhort time, by this <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> be utterly razed down. The Sun may ſhine, and yet not be ſeen, becauſe it is under a cloud. I am perſwaded the great works of the last day are upon us, and the Spirit <hi>is moving upon the face of the waters,</hi> howbeit <hi>darkneſs covereth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115310:4"/>
But to the end I may not be miſtaken, when I ſpeak of the <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> I would not be underſtood as fixing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons or Time: For howſoever, (as I ſaid before) the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> (I think) is begun among us, yet for the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> whom the Lord will make uſe of, to carry on his work, 'tis known onely to himſelf. So likewiſe for the <hi>Time,</hi> though I humbly conceive it ſhall gradually go foreward, and have no more ſuch a death upon it, as it had before; Notwithſtanding, like the Hand of a Watch, the motion may be ſuch, as men looking upon it may not perceive that it turns about.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing at this time, the great Controver ſie is about <hi>Tythes,</hi> awd that there is ſo much writing <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> I ſhall therefore lay down ſome few Reaſons why I think they will not long ſtand, but be taken away, as the firſt <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the Earthquake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Lord intends to have ſomething done againſt <note place="margin">1 Reaſon.</note> Tithes, I have cauſe to think ſo, in that there hath been diſcovered of late, ſuch horrid Oppreſſion and Cruelty in <hi>Tythe-Takers,</hi> as I think the like was never heard of in any former Generation. In truth, it is almoſt incredible what inhumane and most unchriſtian cruelty hath been lotely exerciſed upon many poor people, for refuſing (of conſcience) to pay Tythes. Now doubtleſs this is for ſome good end; I ſay, there is ſomething in it, that the Lord ſhould juſt now bring ſuch things to light: for if we obſerve his wayes of old; <hi>Such wickedneſs as he brought to light by wonderful Providence, he ſoon after puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed moſt ſeverely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſeems to be by the godly on all ſides, a great deſire to have all <hi>ignorant and ſcandalous Miniſters reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Reaſon.</note> Now I think by this time, it doth appear to every one that underſtands the preſent ſtate of the Nation, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb facs="tcp:115310:4"/>
it is, that ſuch unſavory ſalt ſhould <hi>be caſt out to the dunghil,</hi> while Tythes do ſtand. Thoſe that would be rid of <hi>Rooks,</hi> for the hurt and annoyance they do them, deſtroy their Neſt, If <hi>England</hi> be ever freed of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean <hi>Birds,</hi> viz. <hi>ignorant and ſcandalous Prieſts,</hi> Tythes muſt be taken away: for the truth is, this is that which keeps them in publick places, as the Neſt doth the Rook. I cannot but wonder that ſuch who pretend to a godly and Goſpel-Miniſtry ſhould plead for Tythes, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering (and they cannot but ſee it, if they will open their eyes) that ſo long as ſuch a way of maintenance ſtands, moſt unworthy wretches will creep into publick places, what care ſoever be taken to prevent it. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. Howſoever ſome men have very little hope <note place="margin">3 Reaſon.</note> (as things now ſtand) that this <hi>Parliament</hi> will take them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; yet this I ſay, (whatever they do or not do) many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be given why the contrary may be expected from them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is well known that ſuch as are the <hi>Parliaments</hi> beſt and real Friends, and have at all times adhered to them, have not onely often declared their diſſatisfaction concerning Tythes, but ſhewed in many particulars, what a grievous burden and oppreſſion they are to the Nation. <hi>Alexander</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>His truſty Friends were his chiefeſt Treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whatſoever encouragement is given to the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Tythes, yet this we know, they who cry out loudeſt for them, are (for the most part) for a <hi>Single Perſon, or</hi> for them, Intereſt of <hi>Charles</hi> Stuart: I ſay, more a great deal for a King then a free Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ingratus, ſi non, quiſquis amatur, amat.</hi> I much queſtion whether <hi>the eſtabliſhing of Tythes</hi> will ever bring over the <hi>National Clergy</hi> heartily to
<pb facs="tcp:115310:5"/>
this preſent Government, or to ſubſcribe affirmatively <hi>ex animo</hi> to a Parliament, without King and Houſe of Lords. Now it is a <hi>State-Maxime, Not to truſt ſuch men too far, whoſe Friendſhip, if you have it, muſt be bought or hired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Never Parliament had a fairer opportunity and more encouragement to do great things for the Interest of Chriſt and his people, and the publick Freedom of the three Nations, then this: both in reſpect of the Army and good people every where. But ſaith the Sluggard, <hi>There is a Lyon in the way.</hi> I anſwer, It is onely feared, and nothing elſe. The ruines of <hi>Babels Tower</hi> ſeem big (they ſay) and very great at a distance: But the neerer thou come to it, the leſſer. <hi>Works of Reformation are Mountains far off; but when Men come to them with Zeal and Reſolution, they are mole-hills.</hi> And this the Parliament knows to be true, by ſome former expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Who can think that the Lord will make uſe of him, and honour him in things of great concernments, if he have no heart for God and his Cauſe in lower and leſſer matters? He that cannot indure the light of the Candle, how will he indure the Suns light? <hi>If thou haſt run with the footmen, and they have wearied thee, then how canſt thou contend with horſes?</hi> Jer. 12. 5. There are things expected, and to be managed by <hi>the Peoples Repreſentatives,</hi> far higher then what at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are under debate. The Lord will do <hi>his work, his ſtrange work; and bring to paſs his act, his ſtrange act,</hi> Iſa. 28. 21. And therefore if we are not fit to do a little, much leſs a great deal.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is thought by ſome, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſees cauſe enough <hi>to take away Tythes,</hi> and intend to do it,
<pb facs="tcp:115310:5"/>
when opportunity ſerves, becauſe they ſpeak in their last Vote, of looking out <hi>ſome better and more equal way.</hi> If it be true what is commonly reported, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>ſome poor men have been impriſoned for non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Groat and two Pence for Tythes; others forced to pay them, that had the Alms of the Pariſh; Poor Labourers that could hardly get bread for their Families, have had their little houſhold goods taken from them; Others forc't to pay 70 or 80</hi> l. <hi>whereas the debt was not above 5 or 6</hi> l. If theſe things, I ſay, be true, and the Parliament upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall finde it ſo, I cannot but think they will conſider of <hi>ſome better and more equal way,</hi> and not ſuffer ſuch crying ſins in the Nation, eſpecially to be practiſed by men who call themſelves the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Embaſſadors of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Beſides, in their laſt <hi>Act of Indempnity</hi> they declare to be much for mercy: new one would think men of ſuch vaſt pity, cannot but take ſome pity on other poor people, who are dayly undone through the oppreſsion of Tythes. Oh let not that be ſaid of them,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dat veniam corvis, vexat Cenſura Columbas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but this to add, and it is to wipe off an aſperſion which ſome would faſten upon us, as if in ſeeking to have <hi>Tythes down,</hi> we ſought to deſtroy the preaching of the Goſpel. To which I anſwer, We are ſo far from ſeeking to ſtop the paſſage of the Goſpel, as that one main end why we deſire the removing of them, it is to have the Goſpel thereby advanced, and ignorant and carnal people the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er turn'd from the Errour of their Wayes. And doubtleſs whenſoever this ſhall come to paſs, the truth of God, and the power of it will more increaſe and ſpread abroad, then ever it hath done ſince the <hi>riſe of the Beaſt.</hi> Again, Though we are against Tythes, yet not againſt a <hi>Godly
<pb facs="tcp:115310:6"/>
Goſpel-Miniſtry,</hi> but would have it in all places (where it is) encouraged; yea, and care taken that the people e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where thorow the Nation, may be inſtructed in a way agreeable to the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I have been often askt by Friends, why I have not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>William Prynne,</hi> in regard there is ſcarce a book which he hath lately publiſhed, but hath my name in it. Now to ſatisfie ſuch and others, 1. I know how to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my time better, and to more advantage (eſpecially being an old man) then to anſwer one who hath no reaſon with him, but rayling; and in his writing is like to one that turns himſelf many times about, but moves not out of the place. All that he ſaith concerning me, is <hi>(Homaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia)</hi> one thing often ſaid over and over. But 2. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he uſeth my name often, and quotes a book of mine, yet I never ſaw any Anſwer that he hath made to my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there <hi>againſt Tythes.</hi> But as Lizards, who out of the open field do run into buſhes, ſo he leaves the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and Caſe truly ſtated, and hides himſelf under a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of frothywords, bitter Invectives, and <hi>old Moth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten Statutes,</hi> not any thing to the matter or purpoſe. What <hi>Origen</hi> ſaid of <hi>Celſus</hi> works, may fitly be applied to his later writings, <note place="margin">Non eſt periculum ut eis ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertuntum ullus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium. <hi>Lib. 1. cont.</hi> Celſ.</note> 
               <hi>There is no danger leſt any faithful man be ſubverted by them.</hi> But 3. That the man is ſo froward and angry I marvel not, being (as is to be feared) under the <hi>ſprinkling of a Vial.</hi> He hath had ſomething of the <hi>mark of the Beaſt</hi> ſo long upon him, as no wonder if a noyſome and Grievous Sore be upon him for it: Neither do I expect (under the pain and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is) but he will more and more <hi>blaſpheme the name of God, &amp; his Tabernacle, &amp; them that dwell in heaven. 4.</hi> And to obſerve here the wiſe mans counſel, <hi>Pro. 26. 4, 5.</hi> thus far I take notice of the man: ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:115310:6"/>
he will be doing, and by the <hi>ten idle Queries</hi> which he put forth the other day, it is apparent his wit lies not that way; I will put this Queſtion to him.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a man hath a fair pool of water in his ground, the which in time becomes corrupted, Weeds grow, Mud increaſeth, and Frogs creep into it. Now to help this, the <hi>Owner</hi> cuts a new channel, and draws the Water out to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, and leaves the filth and corruption behinde. The Queſtion is, (and the <hi>Caſe</hi> is put to <hi>Will. Prynne</hi> in the behalf of the Frogs) <hi>Whether the water be the Frogs, becauſe the pit is theirs in which the waters formerly ſtood, and whether the Frogs have cauſe to croak &amp; foam, as if they had wrong done them; or condemn thoſe Fiſhes for Hereticks, Sectaries and Schiſmaticks, which refuſe the ſtinking Mud, for the other Chriſtal Stream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>pit</hi> we will take to be the <hi>old Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by <hi>King, Lords and Houſe of Commons;</hi> the <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>Mud,</hi> Tyranny and Idolatry of all ſorts and ſizes; the <hi>Frogs, Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and the whole <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> down to the <hi>Pariſh-Clerk,</hi> not excluding the Lawyers; the <hi>Waters,</hi> the juſt Rights and Liberties of the People, in things Civil and Eccleſiaſtical; the <hi>Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> the People, in their <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſomething is already done in cutting a <hi>new channel,</hi> and drawing the Waters to another place, to wit, a <hi>free Commonwealth,</hi> and to leave the <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>Mud</hi> behinde: And here is ſome work for <hi>William Prynne,</hi> if he can leave his <hi>peeviſh</hi> paſsion, and be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a while, to ſhew us what wrong the <hi>owner</hi> doth to theſe <hi>Frogs,</hi> and why they muſt be <hi>Sectaries, Anabaptiſts, Jeſuites,</hi> &amp;c. that prefer the <hi>ſweet and wholeſome waters of Truth and Righteouſneſs,</hi> before the
<pb facs="tcp:115310:7"/>
               <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>Mud</hi> of Tyranny and Idolatry, We will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>William Prynne</hi> the <hi>Pit,</hi> and the <hi>Weeds,</hi> and <hi>Mud:</hi> But the water is the Owners of the ground. And therefore if the Peoples Repreſentatives ſhall go forward in bringing away all the good Water to this other place, I mean a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and leave the Weeds and Mud to the <hi>Frogs</hi> in the Pit, there are not a few will juſtifie their doing againſt all that <hi>William Prynne</hi> can ſay for the Pit, the Weeds, Mud and Frogs.</p>
            <p>For concluſion; Great is the difference among us, about the <hi>Good Old Cauſe;</hi> one ſaith it is thus, and another takes it otherwiſe: Now the way to be patient, quiet, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it is to take notice, that the Lord is coming forth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controverſie. And it will not be long (I am ſtrongly perſwaded) but he will make it clear and certain, <hi>(that he may run that readeth)</hi> whether the <hi>Caſe</hi> which <hi>William Prynne</hi> hath ſtated, be the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> or what others otherwiſe have aſſerted. It was the Lord who by a wonderful appearing decided the Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Magicians;</hi> ſo afterwards between <hi>Elias</hi> and the Priests of <hi>Baal.</hi> I am apt to think the preſent difference about the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> will not be decided but by ſome viſible and eminent hand of God. There have been many Appeals (eſpecially of late) put up to God about it: and I am waiting (and many more) by faith and prayer, for an anſwer from Heaven: that is, ſhortly to ſee ſhame and final confuſion upon whatſoever is not <hi>the Good Old Cauſe,</hi> but cried up by corrupt men, for ſelf-intereſt; and what is the <hi>Good Cauſe indeed,</hi> to be glorious and alone exalted. <hi>Be ſilent O all fleſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord; for he is raiſed out of his holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation,</hi> Zech. 2. 13.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my houſe without <hi>Biſhops<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> at the three Stills, <date>the 13th of the 5th month, 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Canne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115310:7"/>
            <head>AN INDICTMENT Againſt TYTHES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He conſideration of the great oppreſſion that is now exerciſed in this land, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing upon men that intolerable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of Tythes, wich lieth heavy upon, and is grievous to the people of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general; and more particularly to the Husbandmen and <hi>Farmers</hi> of Lands, who after great labor and charges in plowing and ordering their Land, and ſowing their Seed, and maintaining their Family and Cattel, and payment of Rents, and other Charges and Taxes impoſed upon them, wait patiently for a plentifull Harveſt to countervail their pains and charges; but then cometh a <hi>Tythe taker</hi> with his Cart, and ſweepeth away (in the name of a <hi>Tenth) a fourth,</hi> if not a <hi>third part</hi> of the Husbandmans profit: But moſt eſpecially, this <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull payment of Tythes</hi> is moſt burthenſome to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and faithfull Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to obey him and his Commandments. Theſe (I ſay) and ſuch like conſiderations, have incited me to inquire ſeriouſly, and to ſearch out diligently; Firſt, the time <note place="margin">1. The time when. 2. By whom. 3. To whom, and to what end.</note> when <hi>Tythes</hi> were firſt given in <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, by whom, and by whoſe Authority a Law for <hi>payment of Tythes</hi> was firſt eſtabliſhed, and after confirmed. And thirdly, to whom, and for what end and purpoſe <hi>Tythes</hi> have been formerly, and yet are paid in <hi>England.</hi> And of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115310:8"/>
theſe I ſhall ſpeak briefly in order as I have laid them down. And firſt, to the time when <hi>Tythes</hi> were firſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <note place="margin">1. The time.</note> in <hi>England.</hi> I finde it affirmed by ſeveral Authors, that in the firſt <hi>Three hundred years</hi> after Chriſt, no <hi>Tythes</hi> were paid in <hi>England;</hi> but the Prieſts in thoſe times were maintained by the free benevolence and contribution of the people, as <hi>Tertullian, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> do teſtifie. And in the next <hi>Three hundred years,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Danes and Saxons,</hi> Heatheniſm and Paganiſm did totally overſpread this Land, until about the year of our Lord Six hundred, when <hi>Gegory the great</hi> ſent over <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk into <hi>England</hi> (aſſiſted with forty Preachers) to convert the <hi>Saxons</hi> from Paganiſm to Popery; which was effected in the time of <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King of <hi>Kent,</hi> who being converted, was afterward an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the converſion of his Nation the <hi>Saxons.</hi> This <hi>Ethelbert</hi> is reported to have been very bountifull to the ſaid <hi>Auſtine the Monk,</hi> and gave him the Lordſhip and Royalty of his chief City <hi>Canterbury;</hi> but that he gave him any Tythes, or ever commanded Tythes to be paid to him or to any other, or made any Law for payment of Tythes, it doth not appear to me by any Hiſtory: Nor can it be proved that any Law was made for payment of Tythes in <hi>England,</hi> until the year of our Lord 786. And then in the time of <hi>Off a</hi> King of <hi>Mercia</hi> (which was in <note place="margin">2. By whom.</note> the time of the <hi>Heptarchy)</hi> there was a great Council holden in <hi>Mercia</hi> by two Legats ſent from Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> the firſt; wherein (as it's reported) <hi>Tythes</hi> were firſt eſtabliſhed. So that <hi>the firſt Law for payment of Tythes came from the Pope, and decreed onely by his Agents in the Kingdom of</hi> Mercia, <hi>being but a ſeventh part of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and afterwards as Popery increaſed, ſo Tythes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were eſtabliſhed in other parts of <hi>England</hi> by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kings thereof, who out of an ignorant ſuperſtitious zeal (being thereunto perſwaded by the Pope and his Agents) did many things contrary to the Law of God. And this leads me to my third particular <hi>(viz.)</hi> to whom,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115310:8"/>
and to what end and purpoſe Tythes were formerly given, and yet are paid in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is reported, that the foreſaid <hi>Offa</hi> King of <hi>Mercia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3. To what end.</note> was a man of a high ſtomack and ſtoutneſs, endeavouring by wars and bloodſhed to enlarge his own Kingdom; and after many conqueſts, making <hi>Egfryd</hi> his Son a King with him, in great devotion went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where (with the like zeal and example of <hi>Inas</hi> the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> King) he made his kingdom ſubject to a Tribute, then called <hi>Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,</hi> afterwards <hi>Rome-ſcot;</hi> beſides other rich gifts that he gave to Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> for canonizing <hi>Albane</hi> a Saint. And returning home again (about the year of our Lord 795.) in honour of the Saint, and pretending re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for his ſins, built a <hi>Magnifick Monaſtery</hi> over againſt <hi>Verolanium,</hi> indowing it with Lands and rich Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues for maintenance of one hundred Monks: Alſo, in teſtimony of his repentance for the blood he had ſpilt, and the ſins he had committed, he gave the <hi>tenth part</hi> of all his own goods to the Churchmen and to the poor, hoping thereby to expiate his ſins, and to merit Salvation. The next in order was <hi>Ethelwolph the nineteenth King of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ethelwolph</note> 
               <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> who (in his youth was committed to the care of <hi>Helmeſtan</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and by him to <hi>Swithun</hi> a famous learned Monk of that time) took ſuch a liking to the quiet and ſolitary life (onely enjoyed by men of Religion) that he undertook the <hi>Monkiſh vow</hi> and profeſſion, and was made <hi>Deacon,</hi> and afterwards elected <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> But the death of his father King <hi>Egbert</hi> immediately following, by great intreaty of the Nobles, and partly by conſtraint of the Clergy, he was made King, and was by the authority of <hi>Pope Gregory the fourth</hi> (whoſe Creature he was in both Profeſſions) abſolved and diſcharged of his vows. In the nineteenth year of his Reign, remembring his former <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Profeſſion,</hi> ordained, That <hi>Tythes</hi> and Lands due to holy Church ſhould be free from all Tributes or Regal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: And in great devotion went himſelf to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115310:9"/>
where he was honourably received, and entertained the ſpace of a whole year; new built the Engliſh-School, that <hi>Offa</hi> the <hi>Mercian</hi> King before had there founded; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming alſo his grant of <hi>Peter-pence,</hi> and further cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting to pay yearly <hi>Three hundred marks to Rome,</hi> to be thus imployed; One hundred to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hundred to St. <hi>Paul's Light,</hi> and the third to the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo ſaid, that <hi>Athelſtan</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ethelſtan.</note> about the year of our Lord 924. to pacifie the Ghoſt of his murthered brother <hi>Edwin</hi> (to whoſe death he is ſaid to have conſenced) did not onely undergo ſeven years Penance, but alſo built certain Monaſteries, and decreed that <hi>Tythes</hi> ſhould be paid, by himſelf, his Biſhops and Officers, (but not by all his Subjects) hoping thereby to expiate his ſins. Such was the blindneſs and ignorance of men in thoſe times, being ſeduced and led away from the truth by the Pope and his ungodly Agents, being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their hearts, that the Pope had power to pardon all their ſins, were they never ſo great and hainous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edgar</hi> (about the year of our Lord 959) is ſaid to <note place="margin">Edgar.</note> have confirmed the payment of <hi>Tythes</hi> upon as bad a ground as <hi>Athelſtan</hi> did.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Edgar</hi> was a man of a vicious life, favourable to the Monks: he diſplaced the married Prieſts, and brought in Monks of ſingle life to poſſeſse their places: He built <note place="margin">Forty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſome ſay.</note> and repaired divers. <hi>Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>Nunneries:</hi> he was cruel to Citizens, and a deflowrer of Maidens. The firſt act was committed againſt the Virgin <hi>Wolfhild,</hi> a ſacred <hi>Nun;</hi> the ſecond offence was againſt the virgin <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleda;</hi> another of his laſcivious acts was joyned with the blood of <hi>Earl Ethelwold,</hi> that he might enjoy <hi>Elfrida</hi> his wife: And as one ſaith, For the moſt part <hi>ſuch ſeed-plots were ever ſown in the furrows of blood,</hi> as plainly appears in theſe and divers other examples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Canutus</hi> alſo the firſt <hi>Daniſh King,</hi> who being guilty of <note place="margin">Canutus.</note> the blood of <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Edmund,</hi> ſons of <hi>Ironſide,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115310:9"/>
Heirs to the Crown, about the year 1016. confirmed <hi>Tythes,</hi> built the Abby of St <hi>Bennet</hi> in <hi>Norfolk;</hi> and in <hi>Suffolk</hi> he with great devotion built and endowed the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of St <hi>Edmund;</hi> which Saint he moſt dreadfully feared, for the ſeeming Ghoſt of him often affrighted him; for which cauſe, as alſo to expiate the ſins of his Father, he confirmed <hi>Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. Unto ſuch ſtrange illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were the Princes then led by the blinde Guides, that ever made gain of their devotions.</p>
            <p>Many other ſuch like examples I might produce; but the few before mentioned may ſuffice to ſhew, Firſt, <hi>When</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. The time when.</note> 
               <hi>Tythes were firſt given in</hi> England. Secondly, <hi>By whom, and whoſe authority the firſt Law for payment of Tythes in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. By whom.</note> England <hi>was made:</hi> And thirdly, <hi>To whom, and to what end and purpoſe Tythes were firſt paid in</hi> England; not to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <note place="margin">3. To what end.</note> of Chriſt to preach the Goſpel, but to Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Idolaters, and to a wicked, idolatrous ſuperſtitious end, <hi>viz.</hi> for ſatisfaction of the ſins of the Donor, to maintain a popiſh, idle, ſottiſh Clergy, to ſay and ſing maſs, to pray for the ſouls of the Donors, their wives and children li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dead. And as at the firſt Tythes were given to <hi>Maſs-Prieſts</hi> to read and ſing the <hi>Latine-Maſs:</hi> So they have (for many years) been ſince continued for read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Engliſh-Maſs</hi> (the book of <hi>Common-Prayer)</hi> as may plainly be made to appear by the <hi>Statutes of the ſecond year of Edward 6.</hi> and the <hi>Statute of the firſt of Eliz.</hi> and no Law extant for payment of Tythes to Miniſters for preaching the Goſpel: For although (heretofore in the time of the <hi>Biſhops)</hi> a Miniſter preached never ſo often, yet if he refuſed to read the <hi>Book of the Common-Prayer,</hi> he was by the Law to be deprived of his <hi>ſpiritual promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Seeing then that <hi>Tythes</hi> were firſt eſtabliſhed, and ſince continued upon ſo evil and ſandy foundation, and to wicked ends: Therefore they ought utterly to be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and rooted out of this and all other Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, as popiſh, idolatrous, ſuperſtitious, and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to the worſhip and ſervice of God; becauſe God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115310:10"/>
never commanded that <hi>Tythes</hi> ſhould be paid to any man, but to the <hi>Prieſts and Levites onely,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical</hi> Law, in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and not elſewhere; and by the Jews onely, but never by the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>But it is objected by the pleaders for Tythes in theſe <note place="margin">Objection.</note> our dayes, <hi>That Tythes are due to the Receivers thereof by a threefold Right: Firſt, by ancient donation thereof to the Church for maintenance of Chriſtianity, Four hundred years</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Right.</note> 
               <hi>before the Donation in times of Popery: but they prove it not. Secondly, by the Law of the Land. And thirdly, by the Law</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Right.</note> 
               <hi>of God; all which I ſhall (by Gods aſſiſtance) ſeriouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and according to my beſt underſtanding give a brief</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3. Right.</note> 
               <hi>and ſatisfactory Anſwer thereunto in order as they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>firſt (viz. Donation)</hi> I ſhall not need to make <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> any long anſwer, becauſe I have formerly proved, firſt, the time when, and by whom Tythes were firſt given in <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, By whom, and by whoſe authority they were by a Law firſt eſtabliſhed. And thirdly, To whom, and to what end and purpoſe Tythes were firſt given in <hi>England,</hi> and ſince continued.</p>
            <p>If they were firſt given to the Church for maintenance of Chriſtianity (as is by ſome pretended) Four hundred years before the time of Popery: Then I deſire to know who were the firſt Donors of them, and to what Church they were dedicated; whether to the Church of Chriſt, or to ſome Idol-Temple: For I finde it reported by Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> that the Heathens and Pagans (before the converſion of the <hi>Saxons</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to Chriſtianity) gave <note place="margin">In his larger work of Tythes.</note> Tythes to their <hi>Idol-Gods</hi> and <hi>Goddeſſes;</hi> as the <hi>Arabians,</hi> to their God <hi>Sabin;</hi> the <hi>Siphnians,</hi> to their God at <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos;</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> to <hi>Hercules;</hi> the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> to <hi>Diana;</hi> and others, to <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp;c. So that if any man will boaſt of the Antiquity of Tythes to have been Four hundred years before the time of <hi>Offa,</hi> then he muſt claim them by an <hi>Heatheniſh Donation:</hi> for I am confident that there was no ſuch donation in <hi>England,</hi> until the year
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115310:10"/>
of our Lord 786. For in the Primitive times, for Three hundred years after Chriſt, no <hi>Tythes</hi> were paid in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (as I have already proved) although there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians then in <hi>England,</hi> and many Churches ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in <hi>Aſia</hi> and elſewhere: And whereas it is alledged, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great (who was the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) upon whoſe Donation ſome do much rely; I cannot finde that he did ever command <hi>Tythes</hi> to be paid in any place, or to any perſons: But I do read in the Hiſtory of his life, that he beſtowed Houſes, Lands, large favours, and Poſſeſſions upon Biſhops and Prieſts, and large gifts and favours upon Chriſtian people; but no Tythes mentioned amongſt all thoſe gifts and favours. And <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> (who was himſelf a <hi>Roman)</hi> queſtioneth the truth of thoſe large Donations. Yet doubtleſs his bounty was ſo great to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> of thoſe times, that thereby they became proud, covetous, and contentious; the ſeeds whereof were ſo deep ſown, that they are not yet totally eradicated.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>ſecond right</hi> (as ſome call it) which (ſay <note place="margin">Anſwer to the ſecond Right.</note> they) is by the <hi>Laws of the Land:</hi> I anſwer, That I endeavour not to deſtroy, but to maintain the Laws of the Land, which are conſonant to, and grounded upon the Laws of God, and deſire that they may be rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and righteous judgement given upon them; yea, even thoſe which are thought to make moſt for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Statute of the 27 year of <hi>H.</hi> 8. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">1. Law for Tythes.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſters are enabled to ſue for Tythes:</hi> but where? In the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court onely, and not elſewhere.</hi> For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time, I find no Law extant to compel men to pay Tythes, or to be ſued at Law for non-payment of them. But onely a <hi>decretal Epiſtle of Pope</hi> Innocent <hi>the third;</hi> which (ſaith Sir <hi>Edward Cook) was no binding Law:</hi> Alſo <note place="margin">Inſtit. part 2.</note> in the Two and thirtieth year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. another <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> was made eſpecially for the benefit of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Law for Tythes.</note> who before that time had no power given
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115310:11"/>
them to recover <hi>Tythes;</hi> but in that <hi>Act</hi> is a ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo, <hi>That no perſon Eccleſiaſtical or temporal ſhall ſue for any Tythes in any temporal Court, but onely in the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Court.</hi> Thirdly, in the ſecond year of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">2. Law for Tythes.</note> 
               <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> was made, whereby the two former Acts, of the twenty ſeven and thirty two of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and every Article and Branch therein contained, are ratified and confirmed: but upon ſerious conſideration of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of this Act, it will appear, that it giveth <hi>no power to ſue for Tythes at the Common-Law, nor in any Court of Equity:</hi> For in the firſt branch thereof (which is a very imperfect one) it is ſaid, that every Subject of the King <note place="margin">1. Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> ſhall ſet out and pay his predial Tythes; and that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall carry away any ſuch Tythes, before he hath ſet out for the Tythes thereof, the Tenth part of the ſame, or agreed with the Proprietor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon pain of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the treble value, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that it appeareth to me, that the forfeiture given by this Act, is not the treble va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Tenth part of all a mans Corn and Hay, but a treble value of a Tenth part of the Tenth of Corn and Hay.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is not therein declared, who ſhall have, <note place="margin">2. Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> ſue for, and recover that forfeiture of treble value. And no private perſon can claim a forfeiture given by any penal Law, except it be given him in expreſs terms by the ſame Law. Therefore I do conceive, that the forfeiture (if there be any ſuch) given by the firſt branch of this Act, ought to be recovered and imployed to the uſe of the chief Magiſtrate, or of the Common-wealth, and not of any private or particular perſon whoſoever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is not thereby appointed how or where the ſaid penalty ſhall be recovered, as in all other penal <note place="margin">2. Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> Acts it is declared, That the forfeture ſhall be either to the King ſolely, or to the King and Informer, or to the Party grieved, to be recovered in ſome Court of Record, by Action of debt, bill, plaint or information. But there is no ſuch limitation in that Branch of that Statute.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115310:11"/>
Therefore I do call it an imperfect branch; becauſe in two other branches of the ſame Statute of 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. it is enacted and declared, <hi>That no perſon ſhall be convented or ſued for any Tythes before any other judge then Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, in a latter branch of the ſame Act, power is given to ſue at the Common-Law for the penalty forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for not delivering in a Copy of the Libel and ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereupon a Prohibition is granted. And for theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and ſome other Reaſons following, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the makers of that Law never intended that any penalty given by the firſt branch of that Statute, ſhould be recovered in any temporal Court, but (if any place, then) in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court onely:</hi> And I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo to judge, for theſe five reaſons following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe, if they had intended to have given <note place="margin">Reaſon 1.</note> power to ſue at the Common-Law for any forfeiture given by that firſt branch, they would therein as fully have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their meaning, as they did in the latter branch of that Act.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe this Act is called an <hi>additional Act,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 2.</note> added to the two former Acts of the 27 and 32 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and herein onely ſome penalties added, whereof that of <hi>treble value</hi> is one: but nothing taken away by this Act from the ſaid two former Acts; and therefore the Proviſo contained in the ſaid Act of the 32 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. (whereby all men are reſtrained to ſue for Tythes in any temporal Court) ſtandeth ſtill firm, in full force, and unrepealed: And it is, and hath been the opinion of ſome men, that this penalty of treble value expreſſed in the ſaid Act of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. was rather <hi>(in terrorem)</hi> to cauſe men for fear of a greater danger to pay their Tythes willingly, then that the ſaid forfeiture ſhould be exacted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe the Biſhops were at that time <hi>power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 3.</note> in this land, and then ſitting in Parliament; and can it be conceived, that had they underſtood that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intended to give liberty thereby to ſue for that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Common-Law in temporal Courts, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115310:12"/>
thereby to deprive the <hi>Biſhops Courts</hi> of their Priviledges, and their Officers of their profits; that ever they would have conſented to the paſſing of that Act? for it is well known, that they did alwayes endeavour to uphold their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> and to continue and enlarge their own profits, pomp, and lordly dignity, and were more willing to hold Plea in Cauſes that belonged not to their Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, then to abate any of their Priviledges, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, by a Prohibition directed to the Prelates, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Dioceſs of <hi>Norwich,</hi> which is to be ſeen in <hi>Raſtals Abridgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe all the Judges in their Anſwers to <note place="margin">Reaſon 4.</note> the Biſhops Objections, in the fourth year of the late King <hi>James,</hi> acknowledge, that if the queſtion be upon payment, or ſetting out of Tythes, they ſend it to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court</hi> there to be determined.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, becauſe it is moſt fit, that where the <hi>principal</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 5.</note> 
               <hi>(viz.</hi> Tythes) are to be recovered, there the <hi>acceſſary (viz.</hi> the forfeiture) ſhould be demanded; for <hi>Tythes</hi> are the <hi>principal,</hi> the <hi>forfeiture</hi> of <hi>treble value</hi> is but <hi>acceſſary.</hi> Therefore they that ſay, that they ſue not for <hi>Tythes,</hi> but for the <hi>forfeiture</hi> of <hi>treble value,</hi> do but delude men; as if they would teach them to build an Houſe without a Foundation. <hi>Tythes</hi> are the Foundation; for if a man pay his <hi>Tythes,</hi> there can be no <hi>forfeiture,</hi> nor cauſe of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So that it is a meer juggle, and a forged cavil of thoſe men who ſo object. Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in the firſt part of his <hi>Inſtit.</hi> ſaith, That it is the moſt natural and genuine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of a Statute, to conſtrue one part of the Statute, by another part of the ſame Statute; for that beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the meaning of the makers.</p>
            <p>And again, every penal Law is to be taken according to the <hi>letter</hi> of the Law, without wreſting or adding, and not according to mens <hi>various conceits</hi> and interpretations. And ſo King <hi>James</hi> very well told his Judges in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1616. charging them to do Juſtice uprightly, and indifferently, without delay
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115310:12"/>
or partiality; and yet not to utter their own <hi>conceits,</hi> but the <hi>true meaning</hi> of the Law; not making laws, but decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Laws, and that according to the true ſence thereof; remembring that their Office is <hi>jus dicere,</hi> and not <hi>jus dare;</hi> to declare the Law, not to give a Law. And the ſame King <hi>James</hi> in a Speech to the Parliament in the year of our Lord 1607. telleth them, That as every Law would be clear and full, ſo the obſcurity in ſome points of our written Law, and want of fulneſs in others; the variation of Caſes, and mens curioſity breeding every day new queſtions, hath inforced the Judges to judge in many Caſes here, by Caſes and Preſidents, wherein, I hope, Lawyers themſelves will not deny, but that there muſt be a great uncertainty: And where there is variety and uncertainty, although a juſt Judge may do rightly, yet an ill Judge may take advantage to do wrong; and then are all honeſt men that ſucceed him, tyed in a manner to his unjuſt and partial concluſions. Wherefore, leave not the Law to the pleaſure of the Judge, but let your Laws be looked into: for I deſire not the aboliſhing of the Laws, but onely the clearing and ſweeping off the ruſt of them; and that by Parliament our Laws be cleared and made known to all the Subjects. So far King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I deſire, with all mine heart, that you our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, the Repreſentatives now aſſembled in Parliament, and all others that may ſucceed you, would ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſet upon the <hi>regulating of the Laws</hi> of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and <hi>repeal</hi> ſuch as are unneceſſary, <hi>reform</hi> ſuch as are faulty, <hi>explain</hi> ſuch as are dark and myſtical, and <hi>make</hi> ſuch <hi>new ones</hi> as may be to the glory of God, and comfort of all his faithfull and peaceable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will here object and ſay, that <note place="margin">Objection.</note> Tythes are paid in <hi>England</hi> by an ancient cuſtom, and our Law is grounded much upon cuſtom.</p>
            <p>Then I demand who firſt <hi>brought in</hi> that <hi>cuſtom,</hi> (was it <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> not the <hi>Pope?)</hi> and why is not that <hi>cuſtom</hi> one and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115310:13"/>
               <hi>ſame</hi> in <hi>all places</hi> of this Land? and why are there <hi>ſeveral</hi> and divers <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>tythings</hi> in <hi>ſeveral</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes? And why are not all reduced to <hi>one kinde</hi> and manner of <hi>tything</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the Pariſhes of <hi>England?</hi> For in <hi>ſome</hi> Pariſhes the <hi>tenth</hi> of all the Corn, Grain, and Hay is paid in <hi>kinde,</hi> and in <hi>ſome</hi> Pariſhes onely a ſmall ſum of <hi>money,</hi> and in others a <hi>piece of Meadow</hi> is allowed for the <hi>Tythe</hi> of all the Hay ariſing yearly within that Pariſh: Alſo in <hi>ſome</hi> Pariſhes <hi>tythe-milk</hi> is paid in <hi>kinde</hi> every tenth day during the greateſt part of the year, and in <hi>other</hi> places but <hi>two pence,</hi> or (it may be leſs) for a Cows milk for the whole year. If <hi>any one</hi> of theſe <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> be good and warrantable, why are not <hi>all the reſt</hi> made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable thereunto? But if all be evil (as certainly they are) why are they not all aboliſhed? For it is a Maxime in the Law, <hi>Malus uſus abolendus eſt,</hi> An evil Cuſtom is to be aboliſhed. Doctor <hi>Ridley</hi> in his view of the Civil-Law, <note place="margin">Pag. 147.</note> ſaith, That the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> we pay our <hi>Tythes by</hi> at this day, were ſetled upon this Kingdom by the <hi>Popes Legats</hi> in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial</hi> and <hi>Synodal</hi> conſtitutions. And Mr <hi>Selden</hi> in his <note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note> Hiſtory of <hi>Tythes,</hi> ſaith, As <hi>Tythes</hi> are <hi>popiſh,</hi> ſo are they likewiſe a <hi>Relique of Superſtition:</hi> Becauſe given at the firſt out of a <hi>ſuperſtitious opinion</hi> of ſatisfaction for the ſins of the Donor; yea, and as <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly</hi> paid at this day by many ignorant people, who think <hi>Tythes</hi> to be due by the Law of God, and ſo deceive themſelves. Let not any man think (ſaith Sir <hi>Henry Spelman)</hi> that he hath right to <note place="margin">Tythes too hot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Tythes, becauſe the Law of man hath given them to him: for <hi>Tully</hi> himſelf, the greateſt Lawyer of his time, confeſſeth, That nothing is more fooliſh, then to think all is juſt that is contained in the Laws or Statutes of any Nation. Experience teacheth us, that our own Laws are daily accuſed of imperfection, often amended, expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and repealed. Look back into times paſt, and we ſhall finde, that many of them have been unprofitable for the Commonwealth, many diſhonorable to the Kingdom, ſome contrary to the word of God, and ſome very impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115310:13"/>
and intolerable; yet all propounded, debated, and concluded by Parliaments. So <hi>Tully</hi> and the Roman Hiſtorians cry out, That their Laws were often by force, and againſt all Religion impoſed upon the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as it appeareth plainly, as I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhewed, That <hi>Tythes</hi> were by Parliaments eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for <hi>Maſſing-Trieſts,</hi> to <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>ſing Maſs,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>ſuperſtitious ſervices;</hi> and after confirmed for reading the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer:</hi> Therefore an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous gift</hi> and eſtabliſhment, <hi>unlawfull</hi> in the <hi>Givers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull</hi> in the <hi>Actors</hi> and <hi>Receivers,</hi> and therefore ought to revert to the right Heirs of the Donors; and all ought to <hi>repent</hi> of ſuch an <hi>ungodly action.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> proclaimeth againſt ſuch Laws and Law-makers; <hi>Wo be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 1, 2</note> 
               <hi>unto them that make wicked Statutes, and write grievous things.</hi> So alſo in <hi>Micah</hi> 6. 16. God threatneth to puniſh ſuch Law-makers, and Law-obſervers; <hi>The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of Omri are kept, and all the manner of the Houſe of</hi> Ahab. <hi>&amp;c. Therefore ye ſhall bear the reproach of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Statutes of Princes are no excuſe to tranſgreſs Gods Law; God cannot be confined, reſtrained, or concluded by any Parliament. Let no man therefore think that he hath <hi>right to Tythes,</hi> becauſe the Law of man hath given them to him; for the <hi>Law of man</hi> can give him no more then the <hi>Law of God</hi> will permit. The <hi>Law of man</hi> may <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spel.</hi> 173.</note> give a man <hi>jus ad rem, right</hi> to a thing, as to demand it, or to defend it againſt another man; but it cannot give him <hi>jus in re, right</hi> in the thing, to claim it in <hi>right</hi> againſt or without the Law of God. <hi>Right</hi> to the thing is a lame title; they muſt have <hi>Right</hi> in it, that will have a <hi>perfect title.</hi> The Law may make a man the <hi>poſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r or enjoyer</hi> of a thing; but it cannot make him the <hi>very owner</hi> of the thing. The Books of the Law themſelves confeſs, That all Preſcriptions, Statutes and Cuſtoms againſt the Law of Nature, or of God, be void, and againſt juſtice. Now I might here proceed to their <hi>third right;</hi> but before I paſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115310:14"/>
from this their <hi>ſecond right,</hi> (as they call it) I deſire to anſwer one Objection which I have heard from the mouth of a Judge in this Nation, made in defence of the Statute for <hi>Tythes</hi> of 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>But (ſaith he) although ſome are of opinion that the <note place="margin">Objection.</note> Act of 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. doth not give power to <hi>ſue for Tythes</hi> at the <hi>Common-Law:</hi> Yet it hath been the conſtant practiſe and determination of the Judges for many years, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Actions at the <hi>Common-Law</hi> upon that Statute for the <hi>treble value</hi> of Tythes not ſet out; and that a hundred Judgments have been given in that Caſe.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; If ten thouſand Judgments have <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> been given in that Caſe upon a falſe ground, muſt all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Judges of neceſſity follow their example, without a rule to guide them by? Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi> ſaith, That the Laws are the Judges Guides or Leaders, their ſafeſt Teacher and Fortreſs; and we know that Judges opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not alwayes to be taken for ſound and good Law; neither are we ſo to be bound up by them, that we may not receive a better opinion when it is offered. For ſaith Sir <hi>Edw. Coke,</hi> No mans authority ought to be ſo prevalent with us, that we ſhould not approve a better opinion, if any man offer it unto us. And I have already ſhewed how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient <note place="margin">Inſtit. part 1.</note> and dangerous it is, for Judges to judge by Caſes and Preſidents, where there is no Law to guide them, nor a juſt Rule to direct them: For Judges are but men, they are not infallible, they are ſubject to failings: And ſome of the chief Juſtices of both Benches, and others very learned in the Laws of this Land, have erred groſly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hub. de Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go. Thorp. Triſcilian Belknap. Lock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and been puniſhed ſeverely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome by baniſhment and confiſcation of goods, and others by death, as may appear by ancient Records in <hi>Henry</hi> the third's time, in <hi>Edward</hi> the third's time, and in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond's time. But what need I look ſo far back for examples of this nature, ſeeing that there is one to be found amongſt us of late years, yet freſh in our memories, in the caſe of Ship-money, wherein all the Judges that then were (except two) gave
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115310:14"/>
Judgement againſt Mr <hi>Hampden,</hi> contrary to the known Laws of this Land? And of what evil conſequence that might have been, and how deſtructive to this Common-wealth, and to our Liberties, I leave to the judgements of all underſtanding men. For if that Judgement had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued upon Record, and in force, and not been reverſed by the Parliament, it might have been a Preſident for all ſucceeding Judges to judge by in future times; and ſo might we and future generations have been made meer Vaſſals and Slaves to the arbitrary will of our Governours. And for the further manifeſtation of the invalidity of the firſt Branch of that Act of 2 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. I am able to make it appear, that it lay dead, and no <hi>action of debt</hi> brought upon it at the <hi>Common-Law</hi> for the penalty of the <hi>treble value,</hi> for almoſt fifty years after the making of it, and no Judgement given upon it until the fortieth year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> ſince which time, the ſucceeding Judges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided by the opinions of thoſe former Judges, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other ground or warrant for their ſo doing, make it a ſtanding Law.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>third Right,</hi> (as ſome do call it) which, ſay <note place="margin">3. Right anſwered.</note> they, is by the <hi>Law of God;</hi> I anſwer, that ſome <hi>Pleaders</hi> for <hi>Tythes</hi> do cite ſeveral <hi>Texts of Scripture</hi> to prove what they would have: but having ſeriouſly examined and conſidered thoſe <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I do not finde one that will ſtand by them to prove their aſſertion.</p>
            <p>Their firſt Scripture is in <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 2. and 21. 22. to <note place="margin">1. Scrip.</note> prove that <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> by the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> gave <hi>Tythes</hi> long before the Ceremonial-Law was inſtituted; and that God did afterwards <hi>confirm</hi> the <hi>payment of Tythes</hi> by the <hi>Ceremonial-Law,</hi> for the maintenance of the Prieſts and Levites; and that they ought ſtill to be continued for the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwer, That true it is that <hi>Abraham</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> 
               <hi>gave Tythes</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> of the <hi>ſpoiles of his Enemies,</hi> (but not of all his <hi>own proper goods)</hi> and but <hi>at that one time</hi> onely, and no more. And that <hi>Jacob vowed</hi> to give to God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115310:15"/>
the <hi>tenth</hi> of all that he ſhould give him, is true alſo: but <note place="margin">Non ex debito, ſed ex gratia.</note> neither <hi>Abraham</hi> nor <hi>Jacob</hi> had a <hi>command</hi> from God ſo to do: So that it was in them a <hi>free offering</hi> onely, and not of conſtraint.</p>
            <p>Again, If <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> being guided by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> without any <hi>command</hi> from God, <hi>gave Tythes,</hi> and that God (as ſome ſay) approving the ſame, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards gave <hi>a Law</hi> to the Jews, <hi>commanding</hi> them thereby to <hi>pay Tythes</hi> to the Prieſts and Levites, and after <hi>abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated</hi> that Law: Then it is very clear, that by the <hi>taking away</hi> of that Law, <hi>Tythes</hi> are <hi>utterly aboliſhed</hi> and taken away; and men ought not to <hi>ſet them up</hi> again until they have a <hi>command</hi> from God ſo to do, leſt they come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reproof that our Saviour gives to the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Matth. 15. 6. Thus have ye made the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God of none effect by your own Tradition.</hi> And I deſire all men to conſider, that as <hi>Abraham gave Tythes</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and <hi>Jacob vowed</hi> to give the <hi>tenth</hi> of his goods to God, long before the Levitical Law: So alſo <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob offered Sacrifice</hi> long before the Law was given; and ſo did <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> alſo long before them. Muſt we therefore <hi>now,</hi> according to their examples, <hi>offer Sacrifice</hi> becauſe they did ſo? God <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> the Jews onely to <hi>pay Tythes</hi> in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> which Law <hi>ceaſed with</hi> the Levitical Prieſthood; but God never <hi>commanded</hi> the Gentiles to <hi>pay Tythes</hi> in any place. Therefore the <hi>Levitical Law,</hi> or the examples of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> are <hi>not binding</hi> to us <hi>now</hi> in the time of the Goſpel, nor do they <hi>make any thing</hi> at all for <hi>payment</hi> of <hi>Tythes</hi> now, but rather <hi>ſtrongly againſt</hi> them. And how dangerous it is to do any thing in the worſhip or ſervice of God which he hath <hi>not commanded,</hi> appeareth plainly in the examples of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> for offering ſtrange fire, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. 1. So alſo in <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 20. 8, 9, 10. God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>ſpeak to the Rock,</hi> &amp;c. But becauſe he without a command from God did <hi>ſtrike the Rock,</hi> therefore he was not ſuffered to enter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115310:15"/>
enter into the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Saul alſo for not deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Amalekites according to the command of God, <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 22, 23.</note> was deprived of his Kingdom; for this was counted to him for diſobedience and rebellion. Oh that theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples might work upon the hearts of all men, not to <hi>ſet up again</hi> by a Law that which God hath <hi>caſt down,</hi> and we by a ſolemn League and Covenant have ſworn to extirpate, as a Relique of Popery and Superſtition; even that <hi>bitter root of Tythes,</hi> ſo deſtructive to the true worſhip &amp; ſervice of God, to the advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt; and ſo prevalent in promoting of Antichriſt and his power and worſhip; it being one of the ſtrong holds and props of Antichriſt, whereby his Kingdom is upheld.</p>
            <p>Their ſecond Scripture is in the 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 13, 14. Do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
               <hi>ye not know that they which miniſter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And they which wait at the Altar are partakers with the Altar: So alſo</hi> (for ſo the ancient tranſlation reads it, and the Greek renders it) <hi>hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> But Doctor <hi>Gauden</hi> doth not approve of this Tranſlation, but he will have it <hi>(even ſo)</hi> according to the laſt Tranſlation; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he raiſeth ſuch a duſt to blinde the eyes of ignorant men, as that he would make them believe, that <hi>Tythes</hi> are <note place="margin">See what Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to take for their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Matth. 10. 8, 9, Luk. 10. 8. Eſpecially not in Tythes.</note> due by a <hi>divine right;</hi> and that this, <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord or dained,</hi> &amp;c. is a <hi>Goſpel-Ordinance, commanding Tythes</hi> to be paid to the Miniſters of the Goſpel: for he ſaith, That they do import an Ordinance of God, an <hi>Evangelical Inſtitution;</hi> and yet preſently after confeſſeth, that his <hi>Even ſo,</hi> extendeth not to <hi>all particulars</hi> properly Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, which are ceaſed. Then, ſay I, if his <hi>Even ſo,</hi> muſt not hold parallel <hi>in all</hi> that the Levitical Prieſts enjoyed; then it muſt hold <hi>in nothing:</hi> for either <hi>all</hi> or <hi>no part</hi> of the Ceremonial-Law (which typed out Chriſt) is abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But the Levitical Prieſthood typed out Chriſt, and the Prieſts and Levites were maintained by <hi>Tythes;</hi> and that Prieſthood being abrogated by Chriſt, and that legal ſervice ended, the wages alſo by <hi>Tythes</hi> muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115310:16"/>
end therewith. For it is ſaid, <hi>Heb. 7. 12. The Prieſthood being changed, there muſt then of neceſſity be made a change alſo of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. doth not ſay that the Lord hath declared of old, and doth now by him renew it as an Ordinance of God; but it is the Doctors pleaſure to ſay ſo: they are but his own words; and thereby he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth the Apoſtles words and meaning: for I do not finde in the New-Teſtament any <hi>ſuch Ordinance</hi> for <hi>pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes;</hi> and therefore <hi>non-payment</hi> of <hi>Tythes</hi> is now <hi>no violation</hi> of Gods Law: <hi>For where no Low is, there is no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I hope that all true Chriſtians will ingenuouſly acknowledge, that it is not ſafe for men to make a Law contrary to Gods Law, or to renew or eſtabliſh that Law which our Saviour hath abrogated. And here the Doctor having taken a great deal of pains to ſhew (according to his promiſe) a <hi>Goſpel-Ordinance</hi> for <hi>payment of Tythes</hi> to Goſpel-Miniſters; but finding none, he confeſſeth, that the Lord in the Goſpel hath <hi>not given</hi> any direct Precept for <hi>payment of Tythes.</hi> Therefore (ſay I) <hi>Tythes</hi> ought <hi>not now</hi> to be paid: for certainly, if the Lord Jeſus would have had his Miniſters in the <hi>time of the Goſpel</hi> to be <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> by <hi>Tythes,</hi> as the Prieſts and Levites were <hi>under the Law,</hi> he would (no doubt) in abrogating the <hi>old,</hi> have eſtabliſhed a <hi>new Goſpel-Ordinance</hi> for payment of Tythes.</p>
            <p>But there is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>ſame reaſon, right,</hi> or <hi>equity,</hi> that the <hi>Miniſters of England</hi> ſhould be <hi>maintained by Tythes</hi> as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> were, who ſerved conſtantly at the Altar, and were daily imployed in the ſervice of God in ſlaying beaſts, and offering Sacrifice to the Lord.</p>
            <p>For firſt, they were <hi>one whole Tribe;</hi> and if not a <hi>full</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 1.</note> 
               <hi>tenth,</hi> yet <hi>near a tenth</hi> part of the People.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they had <hi>none inheritance</hi> amongſt their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> for the Lord was their portion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115310:16"/>
Thirdly, the <hi>poor,</hi> the <hi>widow</hi> and the <hi>fatherleſs</hi> were to <note place="margin">Reaſon 3.</note> partake of the <hi>Tythes</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>But firſt, the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are not the <hi>hundredth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1.</note> 
               <hi>part</hi> of the people of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, They (or moſt of them) have <hi>beſides</hi> their <note place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>Tythes, Glebe-lands,</hi> and ſome of them a competent eſtate in <hi>temporal fee-ſimple-Lands,</hi> and ſome of them have a good portion of <hi>goods and moneys,</hi> and ſome other <hi>profitable wayes</hi> to gain by.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Few of them <hi>feed the hungry, cloath the naked,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3.</note> 
               <hi>relieve the poor widows and Orphans,</hi> as they ought to do. And therefore how <hi>dare</hi> they pretend <hi>Scripture, Equity,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> for <hi>payment of Tythes</hi> to them, when God hath left <hi>no ſuch Rule</hi> upon Record in any part of the New-Teſtament? Nor did the Lord ever <hi>challenge Tythes of the Gentles,</hi> as he did of the <hi>Jews:</hi> and God is now ſo far from being <hi>honoured</hi> by <hi>payment of Tythes,</hi> as that he is <hi>highly diſhonoured</hi> thereby, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt denied</hi> to be come in the fleſh; and the Levitical Prieſthood ſeemingly <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden and maintained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is further aſſerted by the ſame Doctor, that <note place="margin">Objection.</note> Chriſt chalengeth Tythes as a Right and Due belonging to himſelf, and that he hath given them to the Miniſters of the Goſpel for their maintenance, and therefore are to be paid to the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> at this day.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That when he or any other man ſhall <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> prove this aſſertion by a <hi>poſitive text</hi> of Scripture in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> then ſhall I be ſilent, and oppoſe him no more. But I fear that this will not content him; becauſe he ſtill ſtrongly endeavoureth to prove his Scriptural right, (as he calleth it) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 14. by multiplying a great <hi>ſound of words,</hi> but not according to the <hi>forme of ſound words;</hi> ten times repeating that pregnant place (as he calleth it) 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 14. Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> And this he would have to be <hi>an Ordinance of God</hi> for Miniſters main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance by Tythes at this day: <hi>Even ſo,</hi> as the Levitical
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115310:17"/>
Prieſts were maintained by Tythes in the time of the Law. I deny not that <hi>they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel;</hi> but it muſt be in ſuch a way, and by ſuch means as Chriſt hath appointed them; that is, as the Miniſters of the Goſpel lived in the Primitive times, by the <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence</hi> and <hi>free gift</hi> of People, and <hi>not by Tythes.</hi> For Chriſt and his Apoſtles never had any Tythes or great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages (as the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have) although they preached the Goſpel <hi>diligently from houſe to houſe,</hi> and from Country to Country. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk. 9. 58. Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the air have neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head.</hi> He had not a <hi>great houſe</hi> to dwell in, nor worldly <hi>rich Revenues</hi> to maintain him (though he was <hi>Lord of all)</hi> he had not ſo much money as would pay cuſtom for himſelf and <hi>Peter,</hi> until it was taken out of the fiſhes mouth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 27. And he ſaith, That <hi>the Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord.</hi> Yet many of the Miniſters <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 24.</note> of <hi>England,</hi> who ſtile themſelves <hi>the ſervants of Chriſt,</hi> ſtrive for great livings, fair houſes, dainty fare, and the pomp and pleaſure of this world, rather then to be <hi>rich in good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to anſwer directly to his <hi>Even ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, that the Apoſtles meaning in that place <note place="margin">1 Cor 9. 14.</note> is either wholly miſtaken, or unjuſtly wreſted by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, to make good his aſſertion; for there is not one word of Tythes for Miniſters maintenance in all that Chapter. True it is, that the Apoſtle pleads there for a competent maintenance for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, but not by Tythes (as the Doctor would have it.) God himſelf appointed, that the Miniſters that <hi>ſerved at the Altar</hi> ſhould <hi>partake with the Altar,</hi> and that they ſhould receive Tythes, and ſuch part of the Sacrifices as was not conſumed by fire. But the Office of the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites being aboliſhed, and the Law for Tythes abrogated, and no new donation of the like maintenance made by Chriſt, to the Miniſters of the Goſpel; by what right
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115310:17"/>
can the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> now claim Tythes?</p>
            <p>And further to his <hi>Even ſo,</hi> (which he urgeth ſo often) I anſwer, that I conceive, he buildeth but upon a ſandy foundation: for if he well conſidereth the Greek, he ſhall finde it to be there, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in our Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is rendred, <hi>And ſo,</hi> or <hi>So alſo;</hi> and the word <hi>Even,</hi> is found onely in the laſt tranſlation of the Bible.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, ſuppoſe that the Original may bear that Tranſlation, <hi>Even ſo;</hi> yet that will not prove, that it is a Divine Ordinance, enjoyning men to pay Tythes to the Miniſters of <hi>England:</hi> For I do not finde in any part of the New Teſtament, that God complaineth againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for robbing him of his honor, &amp; Chriſt of his homage, Miniſters of their maintenance, and the People of the means of Salvation, becauſe they pay not Tythes. But ſure I am, that many Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> rob God of his honour by their <hi>licentious converſation;</hi> Chriſt of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, <note place="margin">See Heb. 2. 9.</note> by not acknowledging him to have <hi>died for all men;</hi> and men of their goods, by unjuſtly <hi>exacting Tythes</hi> to <note place="margin">1 John 2. 2.</note> ſpend upon their own luſts. So that it may be juſtly ſaid, that the <hi>taking</hi> of Tythes (and not the <hi>with-holding</hi> of Tythes) ariſeth from looſe principles, and argueth, that ſuch as take Tythes for preaching, without any Law of God to warrant them, are not the true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt: For there is no ſuch agreement between the Old and New Teſtament in point of Tythes, as the Doctor would have men to believe: Therefore I leave it to the judgement of wiſe conſcientious men, to judge whether I or the Doctor do erre in this point from the truth of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Some other Arguments have been alſo drawn from the Scriptures by others, defenders of Tythes; but I ſhall wave them at preſent, and follow the Doctor a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who in the next place goeth about to maintain the lawfulneſs of Tythes for Miniſters maintenance by a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Cuſtom, confirmed by <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Univerſality:</hi> (two ſtrong props or pillars whereupon the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115310:18"/>
Idolatry, and will-worſhip is upholden) but I finde no ſuch cuſtom in the Church of Chriſt in the firſt Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after Chriſt, as it is affirmed by ſome Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: By others, Eight hundred fifty five years, by others Nine hundred; and by others, not until the Council of <hi>Lateran, Anno</hi> 1215. or as ſome others do affirm, that in or about the year of our Lord, One thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, a decretal Epiſtle by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, dated at <hi>Lateran,</hi> was directed to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> that Tythes ſhould be paid to the Pariſh Churches: For before that time, any man might have given his Tythes to what ſpiritual perſon he would: But (ſaith Sir <hi>Edward Coke)</hi> this Epiſtle decretal bound not the Subjects of this Realm, but they allowed the ſame, and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> a Law of the Land: And ſo by the Popes Law Tythes were paid in <hi>England</hi> (without any other Law, until the Twenty ſeventh year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. And I do not read that Tythes are at this day paid for the Miniſters maintenance in any Chriſtian reformed Church, except onely in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And if no cuſtom can commend, what is in its nature evil, or change it into good, (as the Doctor confeſſeth) then a Popiſh cuſtom of paying Tythes in <hi>England,</hi> (although moſt men approve it) cannot be good, nor ought to be followed; For <hi>we muſt not follow a multitude to do evil.</hi> For although Tythes be not preciſely in plain terms forbidden; yet they being no where commanded in the New Teſtament, we ought not to pay them; we are not to do more or leſs in the worſhip of God, then God in his Word hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p>Therefore what Cuſtom hath been brought up and practiſed in <hi>England</hi> by Authority of men, without any precept or rule in the Word of God, is an evil Cuſtom, and ought to be aboliſhed. But the Cuſtom of paying Tythes in <hi>England</hi> was brought up and practiſed by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of men, without any precept or rule in the Word of God: Therefore the Cuſtom of paying Tythes in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115310:18"/>
is an evil Cuſtom, and ought to be aboliſhed. That cannot rightly be called a free gift to God, or to this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, which is by a ſtrong hand and compulſion taken from men. But Tythes are by a ſtrong hand and compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on taken from men: therefore Tythes cannot be called a free gift to God, or to his Miniſters.</p>
            <p>But I intend brevity, and not to trouble the Reader with tautologies, or vain repetitions, and therefore do refer him to the former part of this my Diſcourſe; wherein I have ſhewed,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The time when Tythes were firſt appointed to <note place="margin">1.</note> be paid in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, By whom, and by whoſe Authority Tythes <note place="margin">2.</note> were firſt ſettled by a Law in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thirdly, to whom, and to what end and purpoſe <note place="margin">3.</note> Tythes were at the firſt given, and afterwards continued in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I ſhall leave the Doctor, and proceed to anſwer another mans Arguments, who in one of his Arguments, <note place="margin">Argument 3.</note> drawn from <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6. ſaith; That people are bound to <hi>communicate to their Paſtors in all good things,</hi> (or <hi>in all his goods:)</hi> and then asketh the queſtion, What good things, or goods are theſe, if not Tythes, the Apoſtle refers to? And for proof of his Argument, he refers me to <hi>Beza,</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wereunto I anſwer, that what he hath ſaid, proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> to the point in hand: For the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>not one word</hi> of Tythes in all that chapter. And can it be by any man conceived, that the Apoſtle there intended to command payment of Tythes to Goſpel-Miniſters for their maintenance, and to bring the <hi>Galatians</hi> back to the Ceremonial Law, whereunto he did know them to be too much addicted? and therefore in the third and fifth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that Epiſtle, he laboureth ſtrongly to take them off from the Ceremonial Law: and can it be thought, that he would then in the ſixth chapter refer them again to the Ceremonial Law, for Miniſters maintenance under the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115310:19"/>
Goſpel? If the Apoſtle had ſaid, that by thoſe good things you are to underſtand Tythes to be communicated and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Miniſters of the Goſpel for their maintenance, I would have believed him: but becauſe he ſaith no ſuch thing, therefore this man refers me to <hi>Jerom</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> as if their teſtimony were ſufficient to ſatisfie me where the Scripture is ſilent. The Apoſtle in that place ſaith one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate unto him that teacheth him, in all good things,</hi> not naming Tythes or any particulars. But the ſame Apoſtle ſaith in 1 <hi>Tim. 6. 8. Having food and raiment, let us be therewith content:</hi> And herewith agree <hi>Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian</hi> and others, who ſay that the Clergy were then maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the benevolence of the People, and not by taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And <hi>Cyprian</hi> further ſaith, That about the year 240. the Prieſts had every man his allowance delivered month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>per Sportulas.</hi> And <hi>Origen</hi> in his ſixteenth Homily upon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let us make haſte to depart from the Prieſts of Pharaoh (who enjoy earthly Poſſeſſions) to the Prieſts of the Lord, who have no portion in Earth, for that the Lord is their Portion.</hi> And in his 31 Homily upon <hi>Matthew,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Becauſe it is written,</hi> The Lord hath appointed, that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel; <hi>That we therefore take not occaſion to ſeek more for our ſelves, then our ſimple diet and neceſſary apparel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard alſo a fourth Argument drawn from 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 11. If we have ſowen unto you ſpiritual things, is it a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Argument 4. anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
               <hi>great thing if we reap your carnal things?</hi> From whence they conclude, that thoſe carnal things there mentioned by the Apoſtle, muſt of neceſſity be Tythes: and ſo by wreſting the Scripture for their own ends, wrong both the Apoſtle and the Spirit of God, and would make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Apoſtle there pleadeth for Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by Tythes; where the Apoſtle not ſo much as once nameth Tythes in that chapter, (as I have formerly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:) but ſome men endeavour to draw in Tythes there, by references of the New Teſtament to the Old, making
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115310:19"/>
Law and Goſpel all one, without putting any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them; and ſo by putting them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would have them to hold forth ſo much, and yet they cannot finde a command for payment of Tythes to Goſpel-Miniſters in any part of the Old or new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
            <p>A fifth Argument hath been brought by one, drawn <note place="margin">5 Argum.</note> from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. which (ſaith he) proves a maintenance for Goſpel-Miniſters, with an expreſs reference to the Old Teſtament for it, in <hi>ver.</hi> 18. And that the Evangelical Prophets in the Old Teſtament are for Tythes, as <hi>Mal.</hi> &amp;c. and that expreſs places in the New Teſtament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them without all revocation.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwer, firſt, I do acknowledge, ſuch a <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> maintenance for Goſpel-Miniſters, as Jeſus Chriſt hath appointed them to take, they may lawfully receive: But Chriſt hath no where appointed them to take Tythes, nor doth the Apoſtle in that place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. nor in any other place ſay, that Goſpel-Miniſters ought to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Tythes: Therefore Goſpel-Miniſters ought not to receive Tythes; and ſo this Scripture proveth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for him, but altogether againſt him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That God by the Prophet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 8. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth that the people had ſpoiled him in Tythes and Offerings: But what maketh this for Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by Tythes in the time of the Goſpel? for Tythes were of Gods own appointment to be paid by the Jews, for the maintenance of the Prieſts and Levites, and the poor; and Tythes were part of the Ceremonial Law, which was then in force, and not abrogated; for Chriſt was not then come in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I cannot finde one expreſs place in the New Teſtament, commanding, or confirming payment of Tythes to Goſpel-Miniſters for their maintenance. For the true Miniſters of Chriſt preach not for hire. The Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> in chapter 3. ſets down that as a character of a falſe Prophet, ſaying, <hi>The heads thereof judge for rewards,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115310:20"/>
and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of propheſie for money,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Another Argument hath been brought for Tythes, from <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 21. which proves as little to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <note place="margin">6 Argum.</note> as the reſt of his Arguments do, there being not one word of Tythes in that verſe.</p>
            <p>For the queſtion there is about giving tribute to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi> but that Tythes are there (or in any other place of <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> the New Teſtament) appointed by Chriſt for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his Service and Officers in the time of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or that they are to be paid to him for that purpoſe, I finde no Scripture produced to prove it: but inſtead of Scripture, the teſtimony of <hi>Hierome, Pareus,</hi> and the Annotations on the Bible are alledged; but thoſe give me no ſatisfaction, I muſt have a word from Chriſt or his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And further, I ſay that the ſpeech of the Prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> and that of our Saviour in <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 21. <note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> were uttered when the Ceremonial Law was in force, and before Chriſt had by his death put an end to the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Prieſthood: ſo that this proves nothing for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters maintenance by Tythes.</p>
            <p>A ſeventh Argument is from <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 23. and <hi>Luke</hi> 
               <note place="margin">7 Argum.</note> 11. 42. where, ſaith he, <hi>Tythes</hi> are named.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that thoſe Scriptures do not prove a command from Chriſt for payment of Tythes to Goſpel-Miniſters, <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> (though Tythes be there named) for the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Prieſthood was not then aboliſhed, nor the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law abrogated: from which two Scriptures, whoſoever will derive a right to Tythes for Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, muſt of neceſſity maintain the Ceremonial Law to be ſtill in force: For Chriſt did not then give a new Law for payment of Tythes, nor confirmed the old for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tythes</hi> to Goſpel-Miniſters after his death; but onely confirmed the <hi>old Law</hi> until the appointed time, that he by his death ſhould put an end to the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood,</hi> and Ceremonial Law: For he ſaith, <hi>That he
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115310:20"/>
came not to break the Law, but to fulfil the Law,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he paid Tribute to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And if any man will be pleaſed to view the Annotations on the Bible, (whereof my Antagoniſt ſometimes maketh uſe) he ſhall finde in the Annotation upon <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 42. theſe words, <hi>That Chriſt would not break the very leaſt Commandment, before all things were accompliſhed; but taught them to ſtick to the chiefeſt, and not prefer the inferiour Ceremonies, which muſt quickly be aboliſhed.</hi> So that whoſoever will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that Tythes were part of the Ceremonial Law, and appointed of God for maintenance of the Levitical Prieſthood onely, during the continuance thereof, and no longer; and that Chriſt by his death put an end to that Prieſthood, and ſo to that maintenance by <hi>Tythes</hi> alſo; Such a man (I ſay) may be ſaid to deny, that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh; and then ſuch a man hath not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: For the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 2, 3. <hi>Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: Every ſpirit that confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that Jeſus Christ is come in the Fleſh, is of God: and every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, is not of God:</hi> and this is the Spirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>Another Argument for confirmation of <hi>Tythes,</hi> is <note place="margin">8 Argum.</note> grounded upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 8. where (ſaith the Opponent) the everlaſting God owns <hi>Tythes,</hi> and profeſſeth himſelf to be the Receiver of them, though not in perſon, but by his Miniſters.</p>
            <p>For Anſwer hereunto, I ſay, when any Miniſter of the <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Goſpel can ſhew me an Ordinance of Chriſt in the New Teſtament, whereby he own Tythes, and hath ſubſtituted his Miniſters to receive <hi>Tythes</hi> in his name, and to his uſe, I ſhall believe it: But in the mean time I cannot be otherwiſe perſwaded, but that <hi>Tythes</hi> were meerly ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, appointed of God for the maintenance of the Prieſts ahd Levites during the continuance of that Prieſthood onely, and no longer. And therefore that Prieſthood which was typical and ceremonial being aboliſhed, <hi>Tythes</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115310:21"/>
muſt of neceſſity ceaſe alſo. <hi>For the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, Heb.</hi> 7. 12. So that it appeareth plainly, that <hi>Tythes</hi> were part of the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> and aboliſhed by Chriſt at his death, and not tranſlated to Goſpel-Miniſters for their maintenance (as ſome would have it to be.) And to prove this more fully, I will now alſo produce ſeveral other Scriptures and Teſtimonies to prove the utter abolition of the Levitical Prieſthood and Ceremonial Law (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Tythes</hi> were a part.) The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, That they were under the Law till Chriſt came. But now after that ye have known God, or rather are known of God, how turn ye again to the weak and beggerly Elements whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ye deſire again to be in bondage?</hi> Gal. 4. 9. and <hi>Epheſ. 2. 15. Having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, even the Law of Commandments, contained in Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>Col. 2. 14. Blotting out the hand-writing of Ordinances that was againſt us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his Croſs.</hi> And what were theſe <hi>weak and beggerly Elements, Law of Commandments,</hi> and <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing of Ordinances,</hi> but the Levitical Ceremonies and duties enjoyned by that Law? <hi>And the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, Heb.</hi> 7. 12. I will cite onely one witneſs more, a modern learned Writer, to prove the repeal of the Law of <hi>Tythes:</hi> Doctor <hi>Hall,</hi> in his Paſſion-Sermon, upon the laſt words of our Saviour, at his death upon the Croſs, <hi>Conſummatum eſt, It is finiſhed,</hi> ſaith thus: What is finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Firſt, all the propheſies that were of him in the Old Teſtament, are fulfilled in the New. Secondly, all legal obſervations that prefigured him: <hi>For Chriſt is the end of the Law, Rom.</hi> 10. 4. What Law? Ceremonial and Moral: Of the <hi>Moral,</hi> it was kept perfectly by himſelf, ſatisfied fully for us. Of the <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> it referred to him, was obſerved of him, fulfilled in him, aboliſhed by him. All the Jewiſh Ceremonies lookt at Chriſt, and had their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Chriſt, relation to him, and their end in him. (Thus far he)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115310:21"/>
And hereunto I might add alſo the teſtimony of thoſe two faithfull Martyrs, <hi>Walter Brute,</hi> and <hi>William Thorp,</hi> who deny Tythes to be due by the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> and alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that pious Worthy the Lord <hi>Cromwel,</hi> by whoſe counſel King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth diſſolved the Abbies, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, Nunneries, and all thoſe habitations of an idle, luxurious and adulterous people; and took away all their Lands, Tythes, and great Revenues, and converted them to temporal and civil uſes, to the benefit of his Subjects, as may be ſeen at large in <hi>Fox</hi> his Hiſtory of the Martyrs; whereunto I refer the Reader, becauſe I intend brevity, and not to trouble you with a tedious Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore having briefly ſhewed, how that threefold cord, ſo much boaſted of by the National Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is utterly broken in pieces, Tythes having no good foundation, either by donation, or by the Law of God, or of men;</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ceaſe to proceed any further in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this point at this time; but ſhall leave it to the judgement of all underſtanding men, who are not byaſſed by prejudice, nor blinded by covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And if I have herein declared any thing contrary to the truth of the Scriptures, I deſire to be better informed, and my error to be manifeſted unto me, that I may repent of it, and not perſiſt in it: For, <hi>humanum eſt errare, bellui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num perſeverare;</hi> It is incident to humane nature to erre, but it is a beaſtly property pertinaciouſly to go on, and to perſevere in an Error. But if I have done nothing herein but what I am warranted to do by the Holy Scripture: Then I deſire all men, as they deſire the glory of God and their own good, to refrain from giving or taking of <hi>Tythes,</hi> and from encouraging any man to take <hi>Tythes</hi> as wages for preaching the Goſpel.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115310:22"/>
               <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THere being ſome room left, I thought good to fill it up with an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> taken from the Authors <hi>Major,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Burges's Minor:</hi> And being put together, ſhall leave it to the judicious and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader to judge whether from both, he may not rationally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That <hi>Tythes</hi> are unlawful.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Authour</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> hath proved as cleer as the ſun at noon day, That <hi>Tythes</hi> (as they are now required) were firſt dedicated upon falſe grounds, and for ſuperſtitious and baſe ends, moſt derogatory to God and Chriſt, and meerly to maintain and countenance a curſed <hi>Brood of Vipers</hi> in their lyes and beaſtly vanities So He.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Burgeſs</hi> comes in with the other part, and with great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence aſſarts it: <hi>That Things not appointed by God from the beginning, but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>His Caſe concering the buying of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Lands,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 30, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>dedicated to him, without his order and allowance, is a laying aſide, and a rejecting the Commandment of God, and making the Word of God of none effect,</hi> Mark 7. 8, 9, 13. Yea, he ſaith further, (and let all <hi>Tythe-taking Prieſts</hi> note his words) <hi>If things are dedicated upon a falſe ground, SUCH A DEDICATION IS NO WHIT BETTER THEN THE HIRE OF A WHORE, OR THE PRICE OF A DOG (that is, then Money gotten by whoredom, and the ſale of a dog) brought into the houſe of the Lord, and dedicated to him; both which he abhorreth, and he looks no otherwiſe upon them, then as the offering of ſwines blood, the cutting off of a dogs neck, or the bleſſing of an Idol. And when it can be proved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of ſuch offering in the time of the Law, then alſo it may be granted that he will own ſuch</hi> MONGREL DED'CATIONS <hi>in the dayes of the Goſpel.</hi> Again, <hi>It is apparent</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thoſe gifts to Biſhops, were no longer to be continued then the Function of thoſe to whom they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, remained.</hi> Datur Beneficium, propter Officium: Office <hi>and</hi> Benefice, <hi>are Relatives: like twins, they live and die together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Judge Reader, whether the Doctor be not entangled in his own words, according to that in the Poet:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non eſt Lex justior ulla</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quam necis artifices arte perire ſua.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>For if this be true which he ſaith, then none but <hi>Maſs-mongers</hi> ought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115310:22"/>
to receive Tythes: For no man I think hath the face to deny it, but Tythes came firſt up in <hi>England</hi> for Maſſes to be ſung or ſaid for quick and dead: It was not given as maintenance to a Goſpel-Miniſter. And therefore by the Doctors own confeſſion, <hi>Tythes were no longer to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued then the Function of thoſe to whom they were given did remain.</hi> So that if the Doctor deny the Function of a <hi>Maſs Prieſt,</hi> he muſt (if true to his own principle) deny taking of Tythes: for <hi>like twins, they live and die together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little more out of the Doctor. <hi>Things once given to God by his command, warrant or approbation, may not be al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ned to other uſes whilest the uſe of Gods appointment doth continue: but not all that men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or ſay they give to God. As in perſons, ſo in things, ſuch onely as the Lord chuſeth or accepteth (and none elſe) are holy,</hi> Num. 16. 7. <hi>let men ſay or thinke what they will to the contrary</hi> Here I agree with the Doctor in both points. 1. That things dedicated to God by his own order and allowance, ought to ſtand, whilſt the uſe of Gods appointment doth continue. So likewiſe, things not appointed by God at firſt, but dedicated to him upon falſe grounds and ſuperſtitious ends, ought to be aliened; neither is it any ſin or ſacriledge to buy or ſell them. But ſuch are Tythes, as hath been proved. But the Doctor poſſibly will ſay, He wrote in the defence of the lawfulneſs of <hi>buying Biſhops Lands,</hi> not intending Tythes. It is true he did ſo, and tells us <hi>That Tythes are ſtill due by divine right to Chriſt.</hi> But the man is again ſnared in his own words, and may well cry out
<q>Heu patior telis vulnera facta meis.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Argument which he brings to prove it lawful that <hi>Biſhops Lands</hi> may be aliened, diverted or purchaſed to common uſe, notwithſtanding their firſt dedication, is, <hi>Becauſe there is no warrant in Scripture for the giving of Lands to Biſhops, nor arguments to prove Chriſts acceptance of them, as holy to the Lord: There is no word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the new teſtament, that requireth or countenanceth ſuch endowments.</hi> Ergo. There are ſix par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which he hath for Tythes, to prove them <hi>Jure divino, and are ſtill due</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>by divine right unto Chriſt.</hi> But I deſire all men in all places to take notice, that there is not one word in any of his ſix particulars, which proves Tythes to be Gods Ordinance for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Evangelical Miniſters. I ſay again, and will ſtand by it, He ſhews us not one Scripture in the New Teſtament, that ever the Lord required Tythes under the Goſpel. So that it is apparent enough he hath as little to ſay for Tythes from the Scripture, as for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Lands: and I am perſwaded, ſhould theſe <hi>Tythes</hi> be aliened, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted or purchaſed for common uſe, he and others, who are now great Champions for them, would face about, and undertake that there is no more ſacriledge or ſin to buy and ſell the Tythes of the nation, then Biſhops Lands. And I have good ground for what I ſay: for 1. what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115310:23"/>
he waites againſt the Biſhops, for the alienation of their Lands and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, is as full and direct againſt the Tythes of the Clergy, that they ſhould be taken away. Neither 2. can he juſtifie by Scripture his bold Aſſertion, <hi>viz. That Tythes are the proper maintenance ſet apart for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and cannot be alienated without ſacriledge:</hi> I ſay he can no more make this good by the word of God, then the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops could prove the buying or ſelling of their Lands to be ſacrilege.</p>
               <p>I have onely one thing to add, and it is, Humbly to adviſe all ſuch as ſhall read the preſent Controverſie concerning Tythes, to take heed they are not abuſed. For thoſe who commonly plead for them will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reader (unleſshe do obſerve their craft) by their extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and impertinent diſcourſes, uſing many words, but nothing to the Queſtion. But no man is more wild, and rangeth from the Caſe rightly ſtated, then <hi>Will. Prynne,</hi> We read of one <hi>Doria</hi> the Admiral of <hi>Genoa,</hi> being to fight at ſea againſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> he fetcht his courſe ſo far about to gain the winde, that he could never come to ſtrike a blow before the battle was ended. Their manner is (and here lies <hi>Will. Prynn</hi>'s proper gift, unleſs rayling) to blot much paper with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what was never queſtioned; we have ſometimes a hundred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures quoted to prove Tythes lawful under the Law; another while as many old Statutes made by popiſh Princes and Parliaments, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Tythes; Then the practice of Heathens and Pagans are ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, paying Tythes to their Prieſts. But what is all this to the matter? for what purpoſe and end are theſe things mentioned, if not to beguile an ignorant Reader? <hi>Ego de Alliis loquor, tu reſponderes de Cepis.</hi> They know well enough (or ate very ignorant about the queſtion of Tithes) what they ſpend moſt of their breath for, is not denyed by their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites. But the <hi>Caſe ſtated</hi> is principally thus: And I ſhall conclude with the Argument.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Things not appointed by God, but dedicated to him without his order and allowance, and upon a falſe ground, and for idolatrous and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ends, as unlawful and ſinful are to be removed.</hi> So Doctor <hi>Burgeſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Tythes under the New Teſtament were never appointed of God, but dedicated to him, without his order and allowance, upon falſe grounds, and for Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious ends.</hi> So the Author.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Tythes as unlawful and ſinful, are to be taken away.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115310:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
